when I was a Seminary Student back in
Pittsburgh many many years ago one of my
classmates would take time frequently
from his studies
to work at the local educational
television station WQED and his concern
and passion was to have a Ministry to
children
and I doubt if you've ever heard of this
fella but he has made the wearing of
sweaters in video telecasts acceptable
hahaha
it's a wonderful day in the neighborhood
but my wife's out of town and I forgot
my coat so I took a tip from Fred Rogers
today and perhaps we need something to
be a little bit more casual and relaxed
today because the subject we have is one
of the most difficult in the whole
history of philosophy and that is the
philosophy of Hegel
g w f Hegel and Hegel dominated the
scene of Western philosophy at least for
the first half of the 19th century and
perhaps it could be said that the
consequences of his thought shaped the
whole of the 19th century now we recall
that with Emmanuel Khan we were left
with this huge wall the wall of
separation between the numeral realm and
the phenomenal Wow Realm and Kant said
that there was no way that we can get
from this realm to the numeral Realm
now hegel's perhaps most important work
it was entitled The phenomenology of
mind he was responding not only to Kant
but also to some other philosophers in
the early part of the 19th century who
had focused their attention on the
the supremacy of Mind Over the material
realm the so-called idealists such as
ficta and shelling
now what happened with Hegel and with
the whole drift of thought in the 19th
century was attention was placed on the
phenomenal realm and as a result of this
a whole new chapter emerged in the
history of philosophy and this new
chapter in the history of philosophy was
that philosophy began to move away from
pre being preoccupied with issues of
metaphysics and epistemology and now
focused its attention on the meaning of
human experience experience that takes
place in this realm
now to simplify that what emerged was an
attempt to construct
in the history of philosophy
a philosophy of History
this is what dominated the thinking of
Hegel and certainly his successor Carl
marks the whole question was what is the
significance and the meaning of the sum
total of Human Experience not only my
experience and your experience but the
experience of the race in our experience
of History
now Hegel developed what was called
a dialectical view of History
a dialectical view of history and we can
call hegel's philosophy
dialectical idealism now for many people
they've never heard that term before
dialectical idealism but they probably
have heard a term that's that's very
close to it called dialectical
materialism which is the sophisticated
title for the philosophy of Karl Marx
now as I say this whole system that
Hegel developed is one of the most
complex and difficult systems of
philosophy that the world has ever been
asked to digest
again when I was in in graduate school
in Amsterdam after I went to Europe in
May and spent the entire summer studying
the Dutch language the very first
lecture that I had to attend at the
University was a lecture in a philosophy
course I was taking on Hegel
at the end of the lecture the professor
being very kind and gracious came up to
me knowing that I was an American
student and so on and he said to me how
did it go with Hegel
or he asked me how did it go you know
with being able to translate what he was
saying and I said
that is I found it very difficult
of course what I meant was it was
difficult for me to follow a professor
lecturing in a foreign language in my
first baptism in it and he shook his
head and smiled and he said yeah he said
Hegel hay is
that is Hegel is difficult in any
language so I I don't appreciate Hegel
for having put me in that embarrassing
situation in graduate school but again
once the attention was on the phenomenal
world
on this world
what happened as a result of this was
that the locus of attention for
philosophy and theology in the 19th
century was on what's called eminentism
as opposed to Transcendence
before Kant
and before Kant put up this barrier
between this world and the next
the overarching emphasis in Christian
theology was on the Transcendence of God
that God must always be differentiated
from his creation the church is believed
that God was imminent in the sense of
being present in the world through his
Holy Spirit by way of creation through
his Providence and through history and
so on but at the same time history was
never ever to be confused with God and
creation was never to be confused with
God there was this absolute distinction
between the Transcendent being of God
and the created structure of his work
but now in 19th century philosophy that
significant difference between the
Transcendent God and His creation begins
to become obscured and one of the most
important
philosophers to bring that about was
Hegel who becomes the Chief Architect in
the 19th century for a philosophy of
imminentism in the German it was it
speaks of God's being decided or the
decided height from God which literally
means this sidedness now
where Hegel differed sharply from Kant
was this where Kant showed that
antinomies or contradictions or tensions
between various views of reality
drove Kant to skepticism and agnosticism
with respect to having any understanding
or knowledge of God
Hegel tried to solve that problem with
his dialectical system
and he sees that
we we can we can't get over the wall
from the phenomenal to the nominal
but Hegel said that distinction
is a false distinction a false dilemma
because in the one sense the numeral can
get over the world or over the wall into
this world and the way the numeral realm
comes over the wall into the phenomenal
realm is by virtue of
uh
God unfolding himself
in and through nature now I'm going to
explain it a little bit more in a second
but we've talked several times in our
study of the history of philosophy of
the so-called subject
object
problem
I am a subject I have a mind and I have
experiences
and my experience is always an
experience of what's happening outside
of myself and that is what we call the
objective Realm
now what the philosophers of all of the
centuries have tried to do is find some
way to reconcile the subjective realm to
the objective Realm
and nobody has really been able to
solve the problem that's inherent in
that
well
the earlier idealists
tried to reduce everything to the
subjective side so that the objective
realm the outside realm is simply a
projection of the Mind
and doesn't really exist
or some have tried to say that the mind
is simply a part of the material world
and it doesn't exist in other words when
people try to solve the tension between
the external world and the internal
world the tendency or the trend is to do
what
is to go to one pole or the other and
let that poll swallow up the other one
well again
the way
Hegel constructed his philosophy of
History was through this process called
the dialectic and the dialectic works
like this
in all the different areas of human
experience that we have such as art
philosophy theology music economics
physics astronomy whatever
we find a process
taking place
that involves tensions that are overcome
in the plane or on the plane of history
and it goes like this somebody will come
up with a thesis
like Parmenides everything is being
and that thesis invariably evokes
an antithesis that is a theory that is
in polar tension to it such as we saw
with
heraclitus and
Parmenides one said everything is being
the other one said no everything is
becoming
so now the progress of philosophical
development is
stifled and it's it there's a blockade
here because you can't get past this
tension until somebody comes along and
resolves the problem by creating what is
called a synthesis
and we saw that for example when Plato
sought to reconcile Parmenides and
heraclitus by creating his synthetic
philosophy of of the two Realms and so
on and then that synthesis becomes the
new thesis
and invariably that thesis provokes what
another antithesis
such as we saw with Aristotle
challenging Plato
now then what happens is that this
creates a a roadblock for a certain
period of time until somebody else comes
along and takes ideas from both of these
sides Works them out together and
creates another synthesis
now of course what happens with that
synthesis is that new paradigm or that
new system or that new philosophical
Viewpoint becomes the basis for a new
thesis and what does that do it provokes
what Roger
what would you guess another what
antithesis that's right you got it
and
and as you can see I'm running out of
Blackboard space here but this then is
resolved in another synthesis and we can
see this pattern go on and on and on
well it's much more complicated than
than this simple illustration I've just
given to you here with respect to
philosophy but you also have the
relationship between philosophy between
religion for example and art and there's
a tension there which is then resolved
in philosophy and then you have conflict
between philosophy and science which is
then resolved in in political Theory and
so on and so you have a whole grid of
these
dialectics working themselves out and
what
Hegel is looking for in the process of
History
is what he called the alfgahoben
now that's just the fancy German word
for some things being elevated to the
next level you rise above the current
dilemma into the next stage of
development where you transcend the
current difficulty and resolve it into a
new thesis that's the experience the
synthesis is the experience of the alpha
Hoban now let me try to talk about this
in simple terms if you can and anytime
you try to speak simply about uh Hegel
you're taking enormous risks because
there's very little as I said that is
simple about him
take for example music
or art
we're familiar with art history or the
history of music
and we see different movements taking
place for example in art you have
classicism
then you have the response of
Romanticism and then you have
neoclassicism and then you have
impressionism and expressionism and
cubism and all these different advances
and so it is in the history of music I'm
interested for example in the history of
jazz that began in very simple terms
with with the blues and with the Ragtime
beat and and the Turkey Trot and the
cake walk and then you've progress from
there to uh Dixieland Jazz and and then
to Progressive Jazz and so on and these
new Geniuses come on the stage of
history and they push the paradigms of
music or of art into a new Direction
by creating a new synthesis in a sense
what happens with these Geniuses is they
challenge the assumptions of previous
generations
they they see the problem
of the tension that has held things in a
kind of paralysis until they challenge
the assumptions and create a new
paradigm but that's not limited simply
to art or to music it's also true in the
physical sciences as we've seen in the
history of physics in the history of
astronomy always moving away from former
tensions and and trying to seek
resolutions of problems that had been
there in the past now
as I said a moment ago
perhaps the
the most deeply felt philosophical
problem historically is the problem
between the subject and the object
and it's the Supreme problem because the
subject is thinking
about something
outside of itself
the object
and how can you ever resolve that well
for Hegel
the resolution of this problem
is resolved
by his concept of the absolute subject
or the what he calls the absolute
spirit
sometimes this is referred to as reason
with a capital r
now what's going on in this scheme is
this that the absolute spirit
is not
ultimately distinct from the world
the absolute subject who is God
is not absolutely divorced from his
creation
in fact his creation
is himself
which immediately moves us into a kind
of complex view of pantheism
that history does not simply reveal God
but history is God in the sense that it
is the unfolding of the absolute spirit
in time and space
so that what history is is simply the
dynamic of God working himself out
thinking about himself
experiencing himself in space and time
so for Hegel for example
he would not deny that Jesus was the
Incarnation of God
however
if you would say that Christ is the
unique incarnation of God he would have
disputed that because all of history is
the Incarnation of God and all of
history is the revelation of God so you
don't look for a delivered word from on
high from a Transcendent God who
inspires prophets and have them be
conduits of Revelation in a
propositional sense like we have in our
Bible
in one sense for Hegel all Revelation is
General Revelation or natural Revelation
because all of nature is God's
experience of himself
and so in this dialectical way God works
himself out so that God is not an
immutable uh being but he is a God who
is in process in process of development
and the development of God the
development of this process is history
so in a very real sense history itself
is divine
now
this uh this approach as I said is
called dialectical
and that's one of the things that makes
it so difficult because a dialectic
involves a tension between seemingly
disparate ideas
I remember listening
to a conversation the late Cornelius
vantil had with a philosopher from
Holland and Van Tel was quizzing this
philosopher about his views and the man
tell is having a hard time understanding
them and when he would ask questions
this philosopher would say well it's a
dialectic and finally in frustration
vantil looked at this philosopher and
said will you please tell me your
theology just once without the dialectic
so I can understand what you're talking
about
because what vantil is saying is the
contradictory ideas are really never
intelligible
but again for Hegel the dialectic
doesn't necessarily involve an absolute
contradiction but a seeming
contradiction of tension which is
capable of being resolved but it's not
resolved by logical speculation
it's resolved simply by experience
and the whole experience of human
history now the impact of this on the
church was Radical because out of Hegel
came the whole development of the
so-called religious historical School
and the whole emphasis in 19th century
theology liberal theology was on
imminentism
where God was bound up with the world
and his Transcendent otherness was being
more and more obscured in 19th century
Theology and the buzzword in theology as
well as in philosophy of 19th century
thought was the word evolution
which speaks in terms of progress not
simply in the biological realm but in
all of the realm of nature in all of
history there is a progressive movement
and the assumption is as I would say
that the movement is making progress
that you start with the simple and you
move towards the complex and that
movement is always an upward movement as
you build these these Triads one upon
each other everything is moving in an
upward Direction so for Hegel
history is the evolution
of God
himself
is an evolutionary being
and everything is in this process of
development
how this provoked a very strong sense of
optimism in the 19th century with
respect to human history that the world
was getting better and better and better
as more and more problems were being
resolved and questions were being
answered and this world is moving
towards a kind of Omega point of
greatness and Perfection as God himself
is realizing his own potential
in the sphere of human history